Leonard Casper Papers
Leonard Casper Papers
1959-1966
Casper, Leonard R.
1.25 linear ft.
Manuscripts, typescripts, and galleys of Leonard R. Casper's critical work on Filipino literature, with some works by others.
2746148
Biographical History
Leonard R. Casper (1923-2018) was a graduate of the University of Wisconsin, Madison and emeritus professor of English from Boston College where he taught for 45 years. He was the author or editor of numerous books on Philippine literature, as well as several pieces of fiction and two volumes on the works of Robert Penn Warren. Casper taught in the Philippines on five separate occasions, twice as senior Fulbright lecturer, and was contributing editor to Solidarity (Manila) and Pilipinas (Kansas; Arizona State). His wife Linda Ty Casper is a noted Filpino novelist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leonard Casper Papers consist of writings by Casper and writings by others.
Writings by Casper consists of articles, books, and prefaces in the form of manuscripts, typescripts, and galleys.
Writings by Others consists of typescript essays, with one letter written to Casper, and three unsigned works possibly written by Casper.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into two series. Writings by Casper is arranged alphabetically by type of work. Writings by Others is arranged alphabetically by author.
Related Material
See also the papers of his wife,
Linda Ty Casper
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Casper, Leonard R.; Philippine literature -- History and criticism.; Philippines -- History.; Philippines -- Literature.; Educators.; Typescripts.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Leonard Casper, 1969-1971.
Inventory
- Writings by Casper
  - Articles
    - Cultural resurgence in Philippine literature, 1965; annotated manuscript, written for Literature East & West (Box 1)
    - Runaway child: Modern Philippine literature, 1963; annotated typescript (Box 1)
    - The tradition of evasion: The Filipino novel from a teacher's point of view, undated; annotated typescript (Box 1)
  - Books
    - New writing from the Philippines
      - Typescript, 1966; annotated; 7 folders (Box 1)
      - Galleys, undated; annotated (Box 1)
      - Galleys, undated; annotated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - The wounded diamond
      - Manuscript, first draft, undated; misidentified by Casper as written for New writing from the Philippines (Box 2)
      - Manuscript, later draft, 1961 (Box 2)
      - Typescript, 1964; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Prefaces
    - After this exile, Viray, 1965; manuscript (Box 3)
    - Selected stories of N.V.M. Gonzalez, 1964; manuscript (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Literature east & west, vol IX, no. 1, 1965; typescript with contribution from Casper (Box 3)
    - A road into the mountains: A verse play, 1965; publication reprinted from The Diliman Review, Vol. XIII (Box 3)
    - A stun of jewels, Angeles, undated; notes by Casper on Carlos Angeles' work (Box 3)
- Writings by others
  - Aguilar, Celedonio G. / Shaken shadows: A collection of thirteen poems, 1966; typescript, inscribed to Casper by Aguilar (Box 3)
  - Arcellana, Francisco / A worm at heaven's gate: A teacher's view of poetry, undated; typescript (Box 3)
  - Benesa, Leonidas V. / The Filipino novel from 1941 to 1962, undated; typescript (Box 3)
  - Constantino, Josefina D. / Philippine poetry in English and its readers, undated; typescript (Box 3)
  - Tiempo, Edilberto K. / The Philippine novel - From a novelist's point of view, undated; typescript (Box 3)
  - Tiempo, Edith L. / Limits - or chaos, undated; typescript (Box 3)
  - Viray, Manuel A. / After this exile, 1959-1965; typescript (Box 3)
    Casper contributed an essay to this work, which is not included here. This folder includes a single letter from Viray to Casper, 1959.
  - Unknown (possibly Casper) / The angelical salutations of Angelus, undated; typescript (Box 3)
  - Unknown (possibly Casper) / The future of the Filipino novel, undated; typescript (Box 3)
  - Unknown (possibly Casper) / William Styron's Nat Turner, undated; typescript (Box 3)
    This is a review of a book, William Styron's Nat Turner: Ten Black Writers Respond, ed. John Henrik Clarke. The last part of the essay is handwritten.